so i'm i chose a pretty provocative
title today saying forget about
emergence
and i'm going to try to convince you
that it's actually a good idea to forget
about emergence and to forget about
reductionism too and see what we're left
with
okay so i've got to point it to
nope doesn't work at all
worked a few minutes ago
there we go so we're going to start with
a little poll
how many of you have ever heard of
quantum computing
raise your hand
not
know anything about it just have you
heard of it
so it looks like at least a fair number
of you have
how many of you have ever heard that
quantum computing is a lot faster than
ordinary computing
so you know whoever figures out quantum
computing is going to be able to wreck
all of our financial transactions and
all of that put our banks in trouble and
sort out the defense department and so
on okay
so today's questions
are
what's the difference between classical
computing and quantum computing
and they were going to segue from that
into what does this tell us about
perception
uh human perception and perception in
general
and then we're going to talk about what
happens when we just forget about these
concepts of emergence and reduction what
are we left with in studying perception
so
let's talk
uh
about quantum computing but first i want
to put one assumption on the table i'm
going to assume that basically i'm going
to assume that quantum theory is a
correct description of the world
but what i'm really assuming is that two
symmetries of quantum theory are correct
descriptions of the world
and i'll talk about each of those
symmetries as we go through this
and i suspect that we can get quantum
theory from those two symmetries and
nothing else
uh no other assumptions
so we're going with a different clicker
now
okay well as long as i have the laser
pointer on fire i can i can click with
that
that's no problem yeah this still works
brilliant okay
just means i have to wear glasses
so keep in mind though that this is an
assumption and if it turns out that
these symmetries are violated for real
in the world then every everything i'm
going to tell you today is wrong
uh because it's all based on on the
assumption that the symmetries of
quantum mechanics actually hold
uh
so this is a
a very deep as as don was mentioning in
his case a very deep empirical
assumption
is that the universe has the particular
symmetries we'll be talking about
so
let's talk about quantum computing
well now actually no methods of
advancing the slides work
so
let's go a little bit farther okay there
we go all right
now it should work okay great thank you
very much for the rescue
okay um so let's talk about quantum
computing
quantum computing is really very simple
and this is the simplest possible
representation there are many many
representations of quantum computing
they're all provably identical
so it doesn't matter which one we talk
about so we're going to talk about this
one which is simple
the simple version of quantum computing
is you start with a question
and
a unitary process is executed and you
get an answer this is called the
hamiltonian oracle view
it's the model of quantum computing that
david deutsch used to design the quantum
turing machine model
it's provably complete
so anything you can do with the quantum
computer designed any way in the world
you can do this way
so that the heart of this is this thing
i've called a unitary process and
unitary processes are actually the heart
of quantum mechanics
so this is what a unitary process is
it's a process that you can reverse and
get the identity
so the way to think about this
dynamically is a unitary process is a
process that is perfectly time symmetric
so this is symmetry number one of
quantum theory quantum theory is
perfectly time symmetric
evolution is unitary
and i would claim that if you think hard
about what time symmetry means
you will understand quantum theory in an
intuitive way
but you have to really think about time
symmetry because it's something that's
radically
unlike what our world is
typically
and we'll see some of the ways in which
it's radically unlike what our world
typically is
so time symmetry in particular means
causal symmetry so we have a question
we have an answer
and in a symmetric unitary process you
can think of it as a combination of a
forward process that goes from the
question to the answer
and a reverse process that starts with
the answering goes back to the question
in fact there's a beautiful series of
papers by giuseppe castiglioni
castignoli sorry
uh in italy
and he has shown
uh
that if you think of a quantum
computation in this way as starting
simultaneously at the question and the
answer and working toward the middle
and ending with the two processes kit
you know like the golden spike in the
railway
then you can completely understand the
speed up of quantum computation over
classical computation
and the way he puts it is that a quantum
computation always knows half of the
answer up front
because it's working at the same time
from the answer backwards in time
and there's a very nice treatment of
this in ruth castner's book the
transactional interpretation of quantum
mechanics which adds some other stuff
that i think is probably not quite right
but she does a nice treatment of time
symmetry in this forward and reverse way
however there's a problem with this
picture
and you all have probably already sorted
out what the problem is the problem is
that these words question and answer are
not time symmetric words in our
vocabulary
right you ask the question first and
then you get an answer it's not we don't
think of that in a time symmetric way
so
the problem is that we've taken some
informational concepts question and
answer
and we've defined quantum computing
by mixing these up with unitary
evolution which is a purely physical
concept that has to do with time
symmetry
and so
we've gotta we've got to to say how
these match up to have a theory that
actually means anything
now technically the last picture i
showed you is completely meaningless
so that let's fix that
by making explicit that
the unitary process acts on some
physical states
some states in the world that are
subject to dynamics
but question and answer are semantic
concepts so what we've done i want to
emphasize the we here some observer
has interpreted this physical stuff
going on
in terms of a question and an answer now
that's a semantic process that's giving
something meaning
so we've constructed a map a semantic
map from something down here in dynamics
world
to something up here in semantics world
and that's what allows us to talk about
problem solving we interpret
something going on in the world as a
question
and then we interpret something going on
in the world as an answer and something
or other has happened in the middle
which we may or may not
know how to interpret or how to measure
anything else
but we know how to do something very
important we know how to say
i'm going to ask a question and get an
answer and then i'm going to use the
answer to be in my next question
and get another answer and get another
answer so we know how to iterate this
process
and when you iterate this process
you get a whole chain of events up here
all of which are semantics
that sort of right on top of this
dynamics down here that you may have no
characterization of at all
but
and here's the second symmetry of
quantum theory your interpretation up
here the semantics what you call things
doesn't change the dynamics that's an
assumption
it's a very important assumption because
without that assumption we can't do
science at all
if what i call this lectern if i call
this a blidget
doesn't change the laws of physics if it
did science would be impossible
every language would lead to to not just
an impression of different laws of
physics but actual different behavior of
the world
so we have to assume that's not the case
uh that's sort of the most rudimentary
uh assumption of communicative
objectivity that you can make that
semantics doesn't change the physics
that means there's no such thing as
physical collapse so you've all heard of
collapse of the wave function doesn't
exist
and i'll show you why and if you're not
convinced by the end of the talk ask
questions in the question period
so what are these induced mappings up
here from question one to question two
to
answer number two here that's just
turning computation that's exactly what
a turing machine is it's just turning
one symbol into another where the
symbols are semantic interpretations of
something or other going on in the world
so for example
you know we can interpret some state of
the world as that equation
and do an operation called addition and
get that representation and multiply and
get that representation we're just
manipulating symbols
but this stuff down in the bottom all
this physics that's going on in your
laptop
or your head or somewhere
okay so what have we learned here we
learned that classical computation is
just a semantic interpretation of
something going on in the world that's
describable by quantum theory
so
in particular this thing is a quantum
computer your iphone is a quantum
computer
there are quantum computers that are
carefully designed so that you don't
realize it
so that you can treat them as perfectly
classical devices that behave in
reproducible ways
the thing is a quantum system i mean on
the inside it's just a bunch of energy
and stuff moving around
okay
so
uh forget about the difference between
classical and quantum computation it
doesn't exist at the physical level
so here's an example
right
uh this thing
is a bunch of energy
and if i look at it
at kind of a small scale i see that
that's the inside of a central processor
of a computer
now when i was a graduate student
we had a computer called a pdp9 in our
lab is about the size of six or seven
refrigerators if you open up the back
doors it looked just like that
but you had to go in there and move the
wires around sometimes
and in the 50s all programming was done
by moving wires around so that right
there was the user interface it was just
you know
twice as big as this area right here
now we have user interfaces that look
like that
you know and i think i'm dealing with
powerpoint and linux and you know a page
viewer or something like that all of
that's just a fiction like don talked
about this morning it's just software
but this stuff is just software too
right we defined this this is something
that we
we configured
the physical world to make it easy to
manipulate for us
we said that's a device but it's really
just a user interface it's an
interpretation of what's going on so we
can generalize this and say any
classical computation is a user
interface or on a quantum computer and
in fact all classical symbols of all
kinds all of language is a user
interface
uh so we're done with the first part i
want to emphasize that i've done nothing
fancy here at all this is old stuff
uh from textbooks this is just standard
denotational semantics
which is the techniques that one uses to
define programming languages and it's
been around forever
uh it all rests on a paper that alfred
tarski published in a philosophy journal
philosophy and phenomenological research
back in the 40s
when he first developed the theory of
how to do the semantics of formal
languages expressed in logical notation
so this is this is ancient standard
stuff and i want to emphasize nowhere in
this talk am i doing anything weird or
new
okay so what does this mean for
perception
so let's look at the usual picture here
usual picture is something happens in
the world
and someone sees it or detects it
somehow or other and they have an
experience
and maybe they do something maybe
there's some behavior so this perceiver
here is obviously a little bit concerned
about what they saw
so we want to look at this process so
let's slow time down a little bit look
at what happens okay so there's an event
and then some information travels
through space
and it whacks the perceiver and it
causes an experience
and then the experience causes a
response
on the perceiver's part
so this is all very classical so let's
look at this again and think of think of
how classical this is
something happens in space and time
information moves at a finite speed
right the speed of light or less
it causally impacts the perceiver and
causes an experience
then the perceiver reacts
now note that is not time symmetric
i have not given you a quantum
mechanical description this is as
classical as the day is long
so let's put this in quantum theory
terms
here's the quantum picture of the same
thing
there's an initial state of the world
in which we have an event and a
perceiver and the perceiver hasn't
noticed the event yet that's just a
snapshot of the world let's call that
the initial state
and
there's a process that acts on this
entire system
to produce some final state which
consists of the
perceiver their experience their
reaction
and if the event is still happening it's
still there maybe it's gone away
uh
but this whole thing turns into that
whole thing
by a unitary process
and remember
these things are processes that are time
symmetric and they're independent of how
we describe them
two symmetries so what's happening here
physically
physically we say that some event
coupled to some observer
evolves through time to
some event coupled to some observer just
at a different time
so i'm writing these things coupled
together that's what that cross with the
little circle means
to say
this is all one thing it's all evolving
together in time
okay and it works both ways
now this is what's physically going on
what's the result
the result
is that this event gets classically
correlated with the experience
that's what we used to say by cause
but there's a correlation now between
the event and the experience or in
information theoretic terms the observer
now has information about the event
okay
so there's a word for this in quantum
theory it's entanglement
there's a physical process going on in
an entangled state with a bunch of
components
and that process as a result classically
correlates
two components of that state
so how many of you have heard of
entanglement
most of you how many of you have heard
that entanglement has something to do
with faster than light communication
okay you're all in good company because
of course einstein himself gave you that
interpretation back in his famous paper
in the 30s
and if you think about entanglement this
way you will never understand it
ever
so
here's the definition
entangled in quantum theory just means
not separable
it's all it means
and not separable means this
it means you cannot equate
the state
of an entangled state with a bunch of
components you cannot equate it to
some
mixture of the states of the individual
components
you can't say this thing is a and b
interacting that's wrong
so read not equals as if i think about
it this way i will get it wrong every
time
okay so what entanglement means is one
physical system with one state
so whenever you hear
uh i have two entangled photons right
that's wrong that's crazy you don't have
two entangled photons you've got one
physical system
with two photons as components
they're not interactive at all
they're just an entangled system
so
let's think about this
let's look at the standard nicolas
geisen type experiment
and i picked gyson because he did this
kind of experiment first
over a separation of about 10 kilometers
about 10 years ago in geneva
and the most recent paper i've seen
which was just uh
1310 so that's this month
uh was from a japanese group we've done
the same experiment over 300 kilometers
so next time someone says quantum
mechanics that's just about little bitty
stuff okay
remember when you thought cells were
little bitty things and then someone
said oh you've got meter long cells in
your legs you said oh white cells are
big like that
so quantum systems are big like 300
kilometers long
so quantum mechanics is not a
microscopic phenomenon it's a
macroscopic phenomenon
300 kilometers is big
so what happens in an experiment like
this you've got a source
and the source emits an entangled state
of something
so maybe it's an entangled state of two
photons two electrons you know in
reality most of these experiments are
done with photons
so the photons come out
and they're coupled in the spin
coordinates so one of them spin up and
one spin down typically easy to make
okay they move apart
and they're two
observers and the observers are always
called alice and bob because it's more
fun than calling them a and b
okay so allison alice and bob have
detectors and they're separated in space
by a long way
and
the photons if you think about it if the
photons are coming from this source
toward
alice and bob
they're going to get
to alice and bob
in the same amount of time or less than
it would take for alice or bob to send a
message to each other
and they'll get there in half the time
for alice to send a message to bob and
bob to send the message back
okay hence the faster than light
confusion so what's going on here
the photons come out of the source
and everything in sight is entangled
right the whole system moves as one
and the light moves a little bit more
it's still entangled a little bit more
still entangled and then suddenly alice
and bob get a signal they say up down
okay now they know they've observed an
entangled state
but it was entangled all along right
what else and bob know is absolutely
irrelevant to the physics
that's the symmetry what we call it
doesn't matter
okay
so here's the message of entanglement
this is what quantum mechanics has been
trying to tell us for 80 years and we're
like this okay we don't want to hear it
right
it's trying to tell us there are no
boundaries
the universe is an entangled system
there's just one thing and it evolves
through time in quotation marks now
as one single system
now physicists hate this
why
i mean this is what quantum mechanics is
telling us why is it a problem it's a
problem because it makes it very very
hard to say what an experiment is
right physicist wants to say okay we're
going to manipulate the world somehow or
other and see what happens
but if the whole thing moves as one
no manipulation going on
and you know physicists are little bitty
things
and the rest of the universe is a really
big thing
so if anything at all is going on in
experiments nature is manipulating us
right us manipulating nature that's
nonsense it's crazy it's silly
right nature manipulates us when we do
an experiment
and physicists call this
conspiracy that nature is only going to
reveal what she wants to well of course
okay
but there's a lovely article by uh
gerard stuhoft a couple of months ago
again on the archive it's not published
yet
um and in this article he basically says
conspiracy is just the way it is gang
get used to it
and he has a nobel prize so he's much
much smarter than i am
but that's the message in any rate and
it's good that that it's being said by
people who are taken seriously so let's
do gysen's experiment again keeping in
mind that everything is one quantum
state so it's entangled still entangled
still entangled still entangled
and this business of knowledge is
irrelevant
alice and bob don't know they're
entangled for a long time but they're
entangled through the entire process
okay
so here's our result entanglement is how
classical information is transferred
from one place to another
so entanglement is what implements
perception
it's the one mechanism we have within
quantum mechanics to implement
perception
and it implements it all the time
ah it says okay
this thing over here is entangled with
that thing over there so we will
exchange some classical information
and note that that's relative it's
always relative to the specification of
a coordinate system
and by the way
this uh perceiver perceived boundary
there's no boundaries in physics so that
boundary is just semantics
including my boundary with you your
boundary with your chair all that's
semantics
okay so let's put this all together
almost done with the second third of the
talk so all reportable experiences
the things we can talk about write down
make a movie about store in a disk drive
anything we can report put in a memory
and expect to say the same
all reportable experiences are included
in classical information that's what
classical information is stuff you can
put it in memory
all classical information is semantics
it's just a user interface on what's
going on
dynamics physics whatever you want to
call it
we are classically correlated with the
world so we can get information we can
learn something
by entanglement
and the boundaries that separate the us
from the world are just part of our user
interface so i want to reference don
here because he's been saying this for a
long time
but
we've at least come to it this way by a
different route that's complementary to
his
okay
so
there's an epistemic bottom line here
oh it says all reportable knowledge all
knowledge that we can tell someone about
or write down somewhere or even just
remember from one moment to the next
even just remembering something from one
moment to the next is making a semantic
assumption
that your memory
now
is the same thing that it was when you
encoded that piece of information a
moment ago
you have any evidence for that
no one does so don't say yes
there is no evidence for that and
there's no way to ever get any evidence
for that
so it's just an assumption that's why
it's semantics
so all reportable knowledge is both
contextual
depends on the specification of some
coordinate system that lets us talk
about entanglement
and it's relational
it's about my relation to something i'm
entangled with
so knowledge is of the form if x
then y
there's no such thing as
knowledge of the form x blanket
statement
all knowledge is implication or
assumption
okay
so that's all nice philosophy so what
well i'll argue that there are three so
what's
okay so here's so what number one
this makes a powerful empirical
prediction
and this is in fact the prediction that
quantum theory has been trying to get us
to take seriously for 80 years
it's
entanglement is everywhere
every experiment at any scale that's
designed well enough should detect
entanglement
so it's no surprise that over the last
five years we've been getting more and
more and more evidence that you can only
understand
human cognition in quantum mechanical
terms
and there are now dozens of beautiful
experiments
but the simple one which you may have
heard of is the pet fish experiment how
many people have heard of the pet fish
experiment
okay pet fish experiment goes like this
i say
imagine a pet
okay so everybody imagine a pet
how many raise your hand if you imagine
guppy
nada
okay
now
forgetting about that question which i
know you can't do
imagine a fish
just the prototypical fish
how many of you imagine guppy
one two all right
so now imagine a pet fish
how many guppies
lots okay
now classical probability theory tells
us the probability of event a
times the probability of event b
is the probability of event a b combined
well we just did an experiment where we
had a really low probability of saying a
pet is a guppy
and a pretty low probability of saying a
fish is a guppy
and a really high probability of saying
a pet fish is a guppy
so we've all in this room just violated
classical probability theory
now it turns out that you can describe
that kind of experiment beautifully
using the mathematics of quantum theory
and you've just created an entangled
state
and now they're now experiments over and
over and over and over again showing
this in different domains and the math
is getting better and
more concepts are being brought in like
entanglement and people are getting
braver
to some extent to say look we're seeing
quantum mechanical effects going on in
human cognition
so i would predict
and and schrodinger could have predicted
i think he did actually at least some of
his writings that we'll see that
everywhere
you know 50 years we'll say classical
probability that doesn't work anywhere
okay
so that's the empirical prediction
there's a methodological prediction
which is
there aren't any parts
so if you go around saying the whole is
more than the sum of the parts well
there aren't any parts
so you're not saying anything
so the whole emergence paradigm is out
the window forget about that
but of course if you go around saying
well we can explain everything in terms
of what the parts are doing
why not any parts
so the whole reductionist paradigm is
out the window too
so we need to forget about most
philosophy of science which is either
emergent dust or reductionist it's just
wrong
i mean if quantum theory is right it's
quantum theory is wrong maybe it's right
but we know that quantum theory is right
that whole kind of thinking is confused
so
if we're going to understand experience
then and we can't use emergence and we
can't use reduction but none of us want
to use reduction anyway
but if we can't use emergence we've got
to study entanglement
and by this i mean
don't just think about it and it's good
to think about it but we need to do
experiments
where we try to understand how human
beings are actually coupled to the world
in quantum mechanical terms we've got a
good understanding of that in classical
terms
but we don't understand it in quantum
mechanical terms at all
and so there's a huge new frontier of
experimental science and they're going
to be experiments that are hard
because
what's nice about classical science is
that you can reproducibly create the
same conditions over and over and over
again
quantum theory tells you that's
impossible you're never reproducibly
creating the same conditions over and
over again so you've got to be really
creative to create conditions that you
can pretend are the same and get away
with it
and when they're doing those experiments
you know very near absolute zero in
fiber optics and all of that they can
pretend that they're reproducibly
creating the same conditions and get
away with it
and
come up with pretty good evidence that
they're getting away with it but it's
harder in psychology but it's something
we've got to figure out how to do
so finally so what number three
is kind of the moral or maybe spiritual
but but i regard it as a moral point
that observers are everywhere
so
that's an observer
you know the system that consists of
my big toe and my glasses is an observer
the black hole in the middle of the
milky way is an observer
uh so there are observers
everywhere at every scale
and most of their experiences are
nothing whatsoever like ours
so you have your experience think about
the black hole in the middle of the
milky way what's its experience like
you're probably saying
who knows well we don't know we don't
have a clue
but we can assume
pretty clearly that it's nothing like
our experience
and i think what that gives us is a
certain amount of humility
uh
to think that our experiential position
in the universe is not privileged in the
least
there's nothing special about being us
there are lots of other systems out
there that have a rich experiential life
they're nothing like we are and their
opinions of things are probably
radically different from ours
so
with that
i'm done
questions
thank you very much chris uh
elizabeth rauscher and i have been
talking about the possibility of putting
a josephson junction
in a new metal
shield
and then having a second
identic virtually identical hopefully
doesn't junction that then can be
modulated as you would
a
a radio wave or a television broadcast
and to see whether the under
superconducting conditions
whether this uh already entangled
state of all observers
would allow for information transfer
that was uh could be considered to be
instantaneous
so that
we would have we could do without radio
magnetic transmissions
i i would guess that you won't transfer
classical information that way you'll
transfer plenty of quantum information
that way
i know you want to transfer classical
information
could you make that distinction more
clear
like can we you transfer useful
information
well i think that's a different
dimension
i mean
they're
at
at a physical level all the information
that we use is
quantum information
uh
so
it's useful to the extent that we've
survived
and can do things
but the information that we write down
in memories
and assume is going to stay the same so
in a sense
all the information that we think of as
cultural
is classical by definition
now the question is
what's the interpretive process
that allows you to say
that a piece of information is classical
it involves making an assumption about
its existence over time
and it's an assumption that we don't
understand very well
and we understand something about how
the brain executes the process of making
that assumption
how that you know i'm the same object
that i was five minutes ago you've
probably all assumed that
but you know no evidence in the world
that says that that's true
it's something that we make up
um
and
so your your question goes to that core
semantic issue of what does it mean to
say that i've gotten a useful piece of
classical information from point a to
point b and there's a very familiar
question in quantum computing because
it's exactly the question
of
i define some state of a quantum
computer as an input
and then i wait a while go have a cup of
coffee come back
and the quantum computer's in another
state
so
is that state that it's now in you know
the two factors of some you know 10 to
the 97th digit prime number
well i can find out in that case by
multiplying the answers together and see
if it's what i define to be the initial
state
but in most cases we can't do that we
have no idea how to do the semantics of
quantum processes
to achieve a ever more refined
many more observations occurring for a
moment
these answers and questions are meeting
and being dissolved through
fun processes
in this evolution
that uh our interest in being able to
communicate instantaneously across space
and perhaps
and
any separation in time is actually an
illusion and so we can actually travel
in those space and time
and commute and communicate
perhaps across these artificial areas
except
if there's no such thing as time i have
no idea what the word travel means
we are um
coming to the end of our time we can
keep going if
because we have a panel on which you are
on coming up if uh if the people that
are setting up the panel want to do that
while you're talking if that you want to
keep taking questions we can do that
um
okay
we can have other questions if we want
all right
thank you chris
a question from a classical psychologist
as opposed to a physicist then
uh your little guppy example
uh if i look at that from the point of
view of let's say a social psychologist
what you did was bias your respondents
by
contextualizing
in the information that you provided is
in your questions
so in since you biased us toward a
certain set of responses
um
can you reinterpret that in entanglement
terms
uh
yeah contextuality is almost another
word for entanglement
uh
and
in actually the
the results within quantum theory
that
um
illustrate the effect of entanglement on
supposedly independent experimental
processes are actually called
contextuality results
in
analog with what you see in psychology
so
i suspect that a lot of classic
psychological data can actually be
reinterpreted in quantum theoretic terms
in these sorts of
effects
many of which we understand to some
extent mechanistically with in terms of
what's going on in the brain we can say
okay
this is a case that actually illustrates
quantum statistics in action
i mean there wouldn't
be contextuality
if we lived in a in a perfectly
classical world
we have another question back here
could you elaborate on the point you the
observers are everywhere and what impact
that has i didn't quite follow
what that means in practical terms okay
um
that's why i carry dwight as a moral
point because we tend to think of
ourselves and you know maybe mammals and
maybe trees as observers
but
we don't think of computers as observers
or chairs or as observers or planets as
observers for example
but if you if you think of observation
as information transfer
uh and you think of information transfer
in physical terms
then
it becomes very difficult
to say
uh what's different
between information transfer in my case
and information transfer and you know a
thermostat's case to take the classic
silly example that philosophers use to
say well you know surely you can't be a
pan psychist because then you'd think
that thermostats made decisions
and
in my opinion the right response to that
say yeah
and there's a there's a wonderful paper
by christopher fuchs who's the guy who
kind of invented quantum bayesianism
he's a quantum computation quantum
information guy
and
um
he says in one in in in this paper
uh with reference to something called
the free will theorem
uh
that
you know does that does his theory
actually imply that elementary particles
are making decisions he says yeah it
does
that's just get used to it
you